# AAKARSH ANAND

**L** 408.813.0119 | ⊠ <u>aanand2@g.ucla.edu</u> | <u>♠ aakarsh-anand.github.io</u>

# **OBJECTIVE**

Large-scale machine learning and statistical modeling for high-dimensional data. Currently, I am working on applications of AI/ML in biomedical data, particularly to understand the genetic architecture of complex human traits and diseases. I have recently published in Genome Research and RECOMB 2024.

#### **EDUCATION**

#### Ph.D. in Computer Science

Sep 2024 - Present

UCLA | Los Angeles, CA

Major Field: Artificial Intelligence

Minor Fields: Data Science Computing, Computational Systems Biology

#### **B.S.** in Computer Science

Sep 2020 - Jun 2024

UCLA | Los Angeles, CA

#### **EXPERIENCE**

Research Assistant Jan 2022 - Present

Advisor: Sriram Sankararaman | UCLA

- · Devising self-supervised approaches for learning useful representations in highdimensional time-series data (in progress)
- Developed a scalable algorithm for detecting pairwise interaction effects between genetic variants on a trait in biobank datasets (Genome Research, RECOMB 2024)
- Leveraged a randomized method of moments statistical framework to build an algorithm for efficient variance component estimation in biobank datasets (preprint)

#### Software Engineering Intern

Jun 2023 - Sep 2023

LabCorp | Burlington, NC

• Designed and implemented reproducible/efficient Snakemake pipelines to analyze adenovirus and phage genetic sequencing data

Research Intern Jun 2022 - Sep 2022

Bruins in Genomics Summer Program | UCLA

 Applied interpretable machine learning strategies to improve understanding of non-linear models of genetic data

#### Research Assistant

Jan 2021 - Apr 2022

Advisor: Paul Boutros | UCLA

- Implemented new alignment method (HISAT2) in cancer sequencing pipeline and redesigned configuration file for ease of use
- · Benchmarked pipeline performance in downstream tasks, created new documentation and diagrams

## **PUBLICATIONS**

- Fu, B.\*, Anand, P.\*, Anand, A.\*, Mefford, J., & Sankararaman, S. (2024a). A scalable adaptive quadratic kernel method for interpretable epistasis analysis in complex traits. *Genome Research*. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2024.03.09.584250">https://doi.org/10.1101/2024.03.09.584250</a>
- Fu, B., Pazokitoroudi, A., Xue, A., Anand, A., Anand, P., Zaitlen, N., & Sankararaman, S. (2023a). A Biobank-scale test of marginal epistasis reveals genome-wide signals of polygenic epistasis. *bioRxiv*.
  <a href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2023.09.10.557084">https://doi.org/10.1101/2023.09.10.557084</a> (Pending submission to *ASHG* and *Nature Genetics*)

#### **AWARDS**

• Warren Alpert AI and Computational Biology Fellow

Jun 2024

• Dean's Honors List | UCLA

All quarters 2020 - 2023

• NSF REU Scholarship | Bruins in Genomics

Aug 2022

• Andy Grove Intel Scholarship | Intel

Aug 2020

# TEACHING AND MENTORSHIP

### Machine Learning Reader

Winter 2023, Winter 2024

Samueli School of Engineering | UCLA

 Provided feedback and grading on students' homework, projects, and exams in machine learning class (CS 146)

#### **SKILLS**

Languages Python, C++

Frameworks PyTorch, Sci-kit Learn, NumPy/Pandas, Git

Other Machine Learning, Statistics, Probabilistic Models, Deep Learning, Pipelines